[Music]
do
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the
90th live episode of ask a budget i hope
you are all doing very well uh as you
know today is a live video chat session
which means that i am going to be taking
video chat
questions by video chat so let me share
the link and as always there are some
rules i hope you guys will
let me show the rules
okay first of all please don't enter the
video chat if you have entered appeared
on video chat before let's give let's
give the
chance to new people secondly only one
question per person please thirdly keep
your questions short don't go on for
hours and fourthly no suggestions please
if you have suggestions put them in the
comments below so let me with that said
let me
share the video chat link
one second
okay where is the link
right
one second
here we are now you should be able to
see it and let me pin it on top
so that everybody can
see it
there you go
so it should be visible now
and let's wait for some people to come
in so
i am hoping there will be more questions
about ukraine about the geopolitical
situation there
uh
i obviously had a live stream about that
yesterday lots of interesting questions
and
lots of new developments have happened
in the past 24 hours since the last live
stream
for instance we are now finding out that
the ukrainians are
being very brutal towards indian
students there
indian students are essentially being
kept in ukraine
as hostages they are being they are not
being allowed to cross over into poland
people of other nationalities of other
european nationalities are being allowed
to cross into poland but indian students
are being beaten up brutalized even
girls are being beaten up and they are
not being allowed to cross over into
poor land
so they are essentially the ukrainians
are essentially keeping the indian
students as hostages and they are
beating them up so yesterday after the
livestream i got lots of comments about
people saying that i am supporting
russia i am pro
dictatorship
i am
you know that sort of thing and we all
stay we stand with poor innocent
helpless ukraine i wonder how many of
you feel the same way today i'm sure
some of you still feel that way based on
principles
well what can i do about that
principles that's not how the world
works on the basis of principles
anyway anyway let's let's uh
let's take some questions
uh let's uh let's bring in mr deepan
show guys if you want me to take your
questions you need to show your faces
okay those of you who are waiting in the
in the wings please show your faces
otherwise i will not bring you in
all right let's bring it
let's start with mr deepancho
hello
last year
uh okay great great great to see you
where are you from kaiser
sir i am from jamalpur madhyavadesh
very nice to meet you sir what's your
question
sir my question is that
when the 911 happened in in america
then american soldier
entered in pakistan and killed osama bin
laden and recently the
u.s u.s army killed isis new commander
in jail i don't know what is what is his
name okay but
we all know about that
the prime is the
1992 mumbai bomb blast
mastermind is living in pakistan then
why indian government is not killing all
of them
yeah good question very good question
the thing is india is still not america
america is the global superpower if they
want they can destroy pakistan next week
they can they have threatened pakistan
in the past to bomb them back to the
stone age and the pakistanis can't
retaliate against america in the case of
india it's a different situation we are
not as powerful as the americans right
we are not
we are a much smaller country in terms
of military power economic power and all
that and secondly
we are right next door to pakistan
pakistan could possibly use the nuclear
option right we will obviously retaliate
and destroy them but we don't want to
lose a single human being in our country
so there are certain things that are
preventing us from taking such actions
right we are still not powerful enough
it's not like okay let's send it's not
like the government has the option that
let's send a person but we don't feel
like sending it's not like that there
are lots of considerations
there is a lot of risk analysis that you
have to do and right now india is not
powerful enough to do such a thing
so that is the reason why even though
the terrorists are sitting in pakistan
as we know very well we are unable to
kill them
as of today
so in future india can do that
in future in the future india will have
to grow grow larger grow more
economically and militarily powerful
become a genuine
local regional or global power then we
can do it not yet not now
all right sir
thank you thank you nice meeting you
good question
thank you bye
okay who is next let's bring in mr
joseph matthew
hello
how are you doing sir where are you from
i'm from
kerala
okay nice to meet you sir what's your
question
um considering the fact russia
it doesn't seem russia will stop at any
cost
so why does ukraine believe that holding
back indians students will benefit them
very good question very good question
this is an excellent question
here's what's happening
the ukrainians they are still hoping
that the western countries will help
them maybe nato will help them in some
way the germans have promised to send
some tanks the french are
promising to send some arms and
ammunition and all things like that so
they are hoping that the more they delay
the russians the more the tide will turn
in their favor and the russians are
being very cautious in the sense that
they are trying their best not to have
any civilian casualties they are trying
their best not to destroy the cities if
they want they can have kiev in the next
60 minutes if they just bomb it into the
dust they can do it they don't want
civilian casualties and also the
russians will never ever harm an indian
citizen
so
the ukrainians are holding our citizens
as hostages on ukrainian soil so that
the russians will be will be stopped or
the russians will have to be very
careful they are using indian citizens
as human shields like saddam hussein did
in the 1990s with american citizens
right so this is the kind of cynical and
evil and cruel behavior the ukrainians
are you are adopting with respect to
indian citizens they know the russians
don't want to touch the
harm a single indian citizen so they are
taking advantage of that and holding
young kids students as hostages
they need to pay for this
so i hope that that experience
yeah yet why is russia being demonized
more than ukraine
because the entire social media is
controlled by the us
right
so and all the media outlets that we
consume in india are all
english-speaking outlets
there is a certain indian tv channel
that everybody loves these days they say
that this channel has been reporting
ukraine for a very long time but please
understand this thing i will not name
this channel
but this indian news channel is not
reporting the indian perspective they
are reporting the american perspective
of the of the war
no news is factual it is all colored it
is all
full of various kinds of agendas and
opinions right so that's how it is so
that's why
the media is not reporting the factual
news they are showing everything as if
in a certain way
you know it's all propaganda it's not
news
thank you okay sir
yeah thank you good question
thank you bye
okay who else do we have um
let's bring in mr avik
hello
hello namaste it's a privilege to listen
to you sir in past two months past three
months i've learned more than
entire life of like not entire life but
in past 15 years in comparison to last
three months listening to you it's been
yes sir
if we were to take pakistan and other
countries let's say after 20 years
what should we our approach how should
we do that
and if you're going to make that
again
adopted from your title
of yesterday's video
right right good question so see the
thing is this right now we cannot make a
khandabara because the other regions
which were in the past part of our
civilization those regions they are now
culturally very different from india and
the kind of culture they have they hate
they despise indian culture
so as of today if we assimilate those
regions even if we can
it's going to cause lots of clashes
and lots of what we call in india
communal riots and tensions and all that
so right now it is not
uh it is not practical even if we are
able to defeat pakistan to reintegrate
pakistan into india it's not practical
right now it's going to change the
demographics of india very badly so what
india needs to do let's say in the next
20 years we are able to end the rule the
the dictatorial tyrannical rule of the
pakistan military what we need to do is
we need to give independence to give
independence to balochistan give
independence to pashtunistan and to
punjab and and keep them under our
protection
and slowly slowly see
akanda bharat may be not possible for
the next hundred years okay we cannot
simply reintegrate the territory because
then we are going to have all this
cultural and religious problems we don't
want that so what india can do is right
now end the tyrannical rule of the
pakistan military which is brutalizing
its own citizens
give independence make two three four
small independent countries out of
pakistan like the americans did in
yugoslavia and in the balkans so we need
to balkanize pakistan first then slowly
slowly
re-civilize them because right now they
are used to the brutal army rule and
they behave like barbarians they behave
like only might is right that sort of
thing so it is a long-term process the
the project of creating a kandhavarata
if we want to do it has to be a
long-term project we are not going to
see akan bharat in our generation in our
lives maybe maybe our descendants will
see it may be 100 years from today but
what we can do is end the brutal rule of
the pakistan army and maybe in the
future
take care of some other countries like
we have taliban and afghanistan which
again is brutal so that's what we can do
it is going to be a long process
so that's what i can say right
thank you sir thank you for all your
effort sir thank you educated me a lot
sir
thank you so much thank you nice meeting
you bye
okay
uh
shall we bring in um
mr vinaisha
hello sir
hello hello hello i am from
i am from bangalore so how are you i am
so my question is in terms of the
military power of russia and ukraine
as you see the air attacks which are
currently happening they say uh the
aircrafts like sukhoi 25
27 35 has been used by russia to attack
whereas in the news the past three weeks
they used to say
that ukraine used to have the
what you call the soviet-era aircrafts
told they were trying to modernize it so
i would i would like to know what is the
current situation if you have any
addition what weapons have been used for
the airstrikes
yeah so the ukraine was part of the ussr
so they have inherited a lot of ancient
soviet era machinery and weaponry so
they have
i believe they have sukhoi aircraft at
least i'm not sure exactly which fighter
what is the model what are the models of
the aircraft that they have but they do
have a reasonably good air force which
has been mostly destroyed in the initial
cruise missile airstrikes so when the
before the russian troops moved into
ukraine there were these cruise missile
strikes that were carried out on various
military installations on airports and
all that by the russians in order to
minimize the fighting minimize the
civilian casualties so i have seen
photographs i don't know where it is
right now but i've seen photographs of
uh
of ukrainian uh airfields that have been
hit by these cruise missile strikes by
artillery barrages and many of these
fighter aircraft that the ukrainians
have or had have been damaged or
destroyed they may still have some of
those but i am sure the russians will
not allow them to fly for long
so
one can assume i don't know what social
media and the western media is saying
but one can safely assume that the first
phase of the attack would be to
neutralize all the air assets of ukraine
and ensure complete russian air
dominance over the ukraine airspace so
the media is reporting so and so fighter
plane is fighting flying in the sky and
they have been
giving out this fake news that some
ghost plane ghost jet was uh shooting
down russian aircraft and all it's all
fake news i think russia has achieved
air control over the ukrainian airspace
and all that remains is to proceed
slowly and take control of the country
so i don't think the ukrainian air force
stands in any significant numbers
and the russians are exercising a great
deal of restraint they have very
powerful weapons that can reduce cities
to rubble in 30 minutes they're not
doing it so
let's wait and watch how long it takes
but i don't see this uh situation
lasting for long but unfortunately they
are using indian students as hostages as
human shields so that's actually one of
the factors delaying the russians yeah
thank you sir it's been good seeing you
having good knowledge and many fields i
hope to achieve thank you
thank you sir thank you thank you thank
you nice to meet you bye
all right
um uh let's bring in uh
let's bring in somebody who has not come
in before let's bring in mr rahul
hello
hello namaste
namaste
i
i said i have two questions you can
answer any one of them my first question
is
like
how we can undo the state formation in
india like right now state formation
had been done on language basis
how we can undo it this is my first
question my second question is despite
having the majority like
current government has too much majority
right now despite having that still like
they are unable to implement laws like
ca is not implemented even
they try to
increase the age of girls that was also
not implemented
why this happens why this is born
able to function
okay let's take question number two uh
why is the government not able to do
what it seeks to do even though it has a
big majority in parliament
well these are there are very
significant and serious limitations to
what we call democracy we believe that
once you elect somebody they are in
power they can do anything they want
that's not the case
there are so many un uh invisible
restrictions that they have to face from
within the country from without the
country for instance we have the
unelected judiciary which prevents the
government from doing lots of things the
government in the
in the previous term
uh they amended the constitution the in
and they brought in the njac act which
is a
reform of the judiciary and the supreme
court just threw it out even though the
consideration was legally properly
changed all the states were taken into
consideration and the supreme court
court just threw that out
is that democratic so you can see
democracy has very serious limitations
in this country and across the world
so if you believe that the government
has all the powers that is not the case
then i'm just giving you one example and
then there are all these ngos in india
which are funded from other countries
which means these are foreign interests
acting in our country and they have the
right to do pls in the judiciary and the
judiciary takes it seriously and then
they issue directives to the government
that so judiciary is one thing and there
are so many other things also i mean if
you do certain things in in india then
uh foreign interests will engineer all
kinds of riots and demonstrations
you have amnesty international we have
various other
organizations that are funded by the
west and by other countries the farmers
protests were engineered from outside
there are so many examples of foreign
interference in india
and if the indian government takes
certain steps then it will be demonized
and uh they will try to engineer a
regime change who knows like they've
done so many times in the past in other
countries so that's why the indian
government right now because right now
india is not a very powerful country our
gdp is just about three trillion dollars
which is a middle level country actually
so today india is not powerful enough to
push back against these foreign forces
who have their agents and their powers
i'm not i'm not specifying anything but
you know they have lots of these things
with their agencies inside india
india needs to rise india needs to grow
more powerful it becomes to become a 10
trillion dollar economy at least
when we reach that stage then we will be
able to push back and it will be harder
for the world to try and criticize india
and try to engineer changes within india
so there are all these restrictions and
problems that the government faces this
is not what indian citizens the common
citizen can see or understand unless you
dive deep into it and you have many
years of experience of seeing the
patterns but that's what it is the
democracy is just in name
it's not really a democracy
that's how it is
okay sir thank you so much thank you so
much thank you nice meeting you thank
you bye
okay
uh let's bring in rishab
hello uh hello sir thank you for having
me have you been here before have you
been have you been on video chat before
sir it was two weeks before
i i have i have clearly mentioned in the
rules please give chance to new people
sir please i'm requesting i want to give
the chance to new people
okay i apologize but i need to
give it to somebody else thank you
i have clearly mentioned in the rules
please don't enter the chat if you have
entered before i want to give chance to
new people okay let's bring in anish
hello anish
hello sir are you able to help me
i can hear you sir where are you from
yes sir hi sir i'm a big fan of yours
the
i am from mumbai maharashtra
so right
basically my uh question is uh you know
uh right now in uh in 2022 and 2021 and
uh basically there are many invasions
like afghanistan has been to convert by
uh taliban then right now ukraine has
been taken over by russia so is there a
possibility that you know china can
invade taiwan to today means uh this
year only and you know take over the
control because it has already taken the
control of hong kong and uh tibet is
already under china so is it possible
that slowly we are merging going towards
you know world war three kind of
situation because one by one you know
one one countries are moving ahead they
are you know like chessboard they are
playing one one countries are going
ahead and
so just wanted to know a view about this
okay so essentially what you're asking
is whether china will possibly invade
taiwan in the coming days right yeah so
okay so see tibet happened a long time
ago in the 1950s hong kong was given
legally to the chinese by the by the
british right so that is again not an
invasion hong kong is not an invasion
tibet happened in the 1950s the only
invasion that's happened recently is
ukraine by russia
and
yeah so it is certainly possible see now
we are witnessing that the nato alliance
has not been able to do much about
ukraine
right uh the americans have essentially
abandoned ukraine even though they
promised them everything they promised
them all kinds of things but they have
abandoned ukraine so we can see the
visible decline
of the western powers that are led by
the us right so it is possible that the
chinese may feel encouraged by that and
they may perhaps decide at some point in
time in the coming days that maybe the
time is right to take over taiwan or at
least attempt an invasion of taiwan
but of course the chinese are also not
stupid they're not fools they know that
america is treaty bound to defend taiwan
so if you start a shooting match if you
start a kinetic war
uh once it starts you don't have control
about what hap or or what happens
so if they do it it could lead to
an escalation a gradual snowballing of
the violence and the fighting which
could
become what you like what you said world
war three once you start something it's
no longer in under your control the
planning and all the all that you can do
once you start you don't you don't know
what's going to happen
so
i don't think world war iii would if it
starts if it does happen i don't think
it's going to happen in europe
because uh
it's it's
going to happen it's most likely going
to happen in the asia-pacific region if
the chinese begin the thing
right now the chinese are in the asia
pacific region essentially to some
extent encircled by the americans on the
eastern side you have japan that's a
ring of that's a chain of islands on the
southern side you have the philippines
taiwan all that so they are essentially
ring fenced by the americans by american
allies they want to break that so it's
up to them when they decide the time is
right but if they do it it's it could
possibly lead to what we can call world
war three on the other hand they may not
decide to do it right now and they may
try to push
put pressure on india by doing it by
escalating the border
tensions and by doing incursions into
indian territory all that it is a
possibility it is likely that the
chinese in the coming days weeks months
months may escalate the border issue
with india it is possible so we have to
wait and watch and we have to be
prepared for these scenarios
thank you sir thank you all right nice
meeting you a good question thank you
bye
okay
let's bring in mr atharva
hello
hello sir they're finally how are you
doing
sir i'm fine sir how are you sir
i'm good where are you from
well i'm from kanpur
nice to meet you sir what's your
question
so my question is that what is the
difference between a civil engineer and
an architect
a civil engineer and an architect what's
the difference a civil engineer is
somebody who
ah that's a good
this is an interesting question
okay what's an engineer an engineer is
somebody who uses the principles of
science let's say newtonian mechanics or
all that and applies that into the real
world so engineers actually build things
engineers are builders
so civil engineer is typically a person
who builds roadways bridges
flyovers railway lines things like that
right so they are involved in the
construction and building and
of of actual
public works
that's that's a civil engineer an
architect is essentially a designer
architects create blueprints of
buildings
of residential buildings of of
multi-storied buildings of office
buildings commercial buildings all that
railway stations
airports all that so architects are
designers they give you the design so
the civil engineer will take the
blueprint that the architect has created
and the civil engineer will bring that
into reality they will actually
construct it and of course they will not
go and do it themselves they oversee the
workers who are doing it but it is the
responsibility of the civil engineer to
actually implement the blueprint and the
design that the architect has created so
that's the difference
okay so if
uh
so it is related to that
only one question only one question
okay rules are also i want to give a
chance to everybody all right yes sir
thank you thank you sir thank you nice
meeting you sir
okay one question per person please
don't try to
to
take liberties yes okay let's let's give
everybody a chance let's bring in mr uh
dhruva
hello
good evening sir
good evening drew where are you from
say
should india send back ukrainian
tourists stranded and go to their
respective homeland
in retaliation of what they are doing to
the indian students there in ukraine
no i think india yeah good question it's
a good question uh they are brutalizing
our people and all that see we have a
certain
culture of our own we do not touch
harmless i mean uh innocent people we
don't harm people unnecessarily i know
that's what they are doing
i would not recommend that india should
take similar actions against the
ukrainian citizens in india and we
should not try to repair to repatriate
them also
what we can do what we what the
government of india needs to focus on is
to bring back our citizens from ukraine
safely and we need to put pressure on
the ukrainian government and if it
doesn't happen maybe we should send some
paratroopers there to liberate our
citizens and to assist the
russians if it's needed and what we can
also do is we can possibly deport the
ukrainian citizens from india at their
expense
so that's what we can do i would not
suggest that we should
take any other action against the
ukrainian citizens because
that's not how we do things right
so that's what i can say that's what i
would suggest
okay so thank you
thank you thank you bye
um
let's let's bring in arijit
hello hello sir
so
uh
okay what's your question no so my
question is uh like in the ancient times
bengal was now the powerhouse of
buddhism it housed vikram shilla and
nalan
and it had monks like katisha who were
you know very influential and had
influences in tibet
and they helped create
tibetan buddhism essentially so my
question is how did this rich tradition
of buddhism come to an end in bengal
like there are only one percent of
bengali buddhists i know just one family
of bangladesh
so i would like to answer
the answer is very simple the answer is
very simple it is a turks so destroyed
buddhism see the talks see first of all
there is no difference between buddhism
and hinduism the british have created
this idea that buddhism hindus are
separate now how did the both the
practices disappear from india is the
question and you're talking about bengal
bengal is part of india so what happened
is this these turks they invaded india
from central asia they came from central
asia central asia used to be
uh
it was it used to be part of the indo
sphere so you have if you look into if
you look at the uh the archaeological
sites in central asia you will find
buddhist stupas everywhere destroyed
buddhist stupas you will also find
destroyed hindu temples that have been
repurposed into other religious
buildings and so on so the turks were
familiar with indian culture in central
asia and the flavor of indian culture
that was really prevalent in central
asia was was what we call buddhism today
so they wanted to disapprove and destroy
buddhism from wherever they found it so
they they were familiar with the statue
of the buddha they used to call it the
booth they called it
so they'd use that word for all muris
for all idols so when they came into
india they
went after all manifestations of what we
call buddhism today and they eradicated
all visible manifestations of buddhism
from india you will not find it it's
rare
to find a single unbroken buddha statue
in in india from that period from a
thousand years or more before because
the turks decapitated all the statues
they decapitated all the monks they
destroyed all the universities where
buddhism or both the dharma was taught
in addition to other things
and that's what they did they destroyed
vikram sheila everything they burned all
the libraries so it is the turks that
destroyed what we call buddhism from
india
they went after buddhism specifically
they had this for some reason a great
hatred for what we call buddhism and
today the our teachers and history
teachers and professors and textbooks
will teach you that it is brahmanism
that that replaced buddhism and uprooted
buddhism that is a blatant lie it is the
turks who did that it is people like
bhakti killed you destroyed nalanda and
killed all the teachers and students it
is people like him and other barbarians
who destroyed what we call buddhism from
india and also from bengal bengal as you
know i had vikram sheila and many other
wonderful places
incredible centers of learning and
culture which were all destroyed by the
turks so that is how it happened
thank you
and uh thank you like your show thank
you
thank you nice meeting you thank you so
much
okay let us bring in
let's bring in whom shall we bring in
let's bring in somebody who has not come
in before if you have come in before
please don't
be here please i request you
let's bring in mr sunil
this is not mr sunil
this is neil neil yeah
hi dean how's it going i'm good thank
you how are you where are you from
um i'm i'm originally from mumbai but
i'm calling from sydney australia
all right nice to meet you sir what's
your question
my question is about indian um our
indian scientist nami narayan
i wanted to know
what about him what was uh what was
happening to him who was behind all of
his
tragedy that was going on with him
um
he was trying to develop a cryogenic
engine uh which was i think so indeed
indigenous through india and making a
lot of developments in indian aerospace
engineering and rocket engineering so
what was going on with him and if his
ideas would have been succeeded where
would have been india's space research
right now
so that was okay good question yeah yeah
dr nambi narayan so i have not studied
this case in great detail what i know is
that he there were allegations made
against him that he was part of some
international spying ring or something
and
he was arrested i believe jailed for a
few years or something i am not very
sure about this i have not studied this
case but yes you're right he was he was
in israel he was part of the team that
was developing the uh
the cryogenic
rocket engine technology
and what happened is that after the i'm
i think this happened more than 20 years
ago this this entire incident
if i'm not mistaken right so um so in
the aftermath of the 1998 nuclear tests
that india carried out
in pokharan the americans our great
friends today apparently they had
imposed sanctions on india they had
prevented the russians from transferring
cryogenic rocket engines to india and
even the technology that india had
purchased from the russians so then
india was forced to try and develop the
technology on its own we had to do it
ourselves and mr narayan was part of
that and to sabotage that effort these
things were done so uh clearly he was
not spying for a foreign power or
anything or doing any such thing it was
all
manufactured fabricated allegations and
he had to suffer for it he had to pay
for it by spending
i don't know how long but he spent time
in prison for that now obviously he has
been exonerated we know that it was all
done uh on purpose it was it was all
fabricated but it's strange
that the indian government allowed that
to happen that they
yeah so so i think the the development
of the technology was delayed by a few
years because of this uh because of the
foreign interference in this and because
the government took this allegation
seriously and prosecuted our own
scientists who was doing our work today
we have the technology we have developed
the technology on our own over on our
own we have the vikas engine and
now we are fine we can we can
do it on our on our own the gslv
mark iii or whatever it is it's powered
by our own tragic rocket engines so i
think the indian cryogenic program was
delayed by a few years because of all
this uh
i'm sure there must be more going on
mr nambin iran is the one that we know
of but there must be other scientists
who are also targeted in this i'm sure
i'm just i'm guessing i don't have the
information but i'm guessing it's an
educated guess that such interference
must have happened so it delayed our
program by by several years and that's
what we suffered
all right got my answer thank you very
much for your time thank you nice
meeting you sir thank you bye
okay uh
let's
bring in sunil yes i was saying sunil
hi hi
for manufacturing the highest quality
fabric for shirts
nice fantastic fantastic nice meeting
you sir what's your question sir my
question is about time dilation
uh so as per time dilation concept the
time on earth can be different the
perceived time on earth
is different than time on some another
planet so my question is
in in interstellar movie they show that
the actor goes on some other planet
and comes back
so he just aged like a few days while
all his
all the people who were on earth they
grew up by more than 40 50 years
so also my question is
i like i feel it's only the pursuit time
which is different on earth than other
catalan
but the biological aging which happens
in a human
is that does that also slow down when
someone goes on some other planet so
does the biological clock also changes
that's my question
yes good question so the the concept of
time dilation comes from a special
relativity the special theory of
relativity which albert einstein put
forth in 1905. so what happens is that
when your velocity increases with
respect to a certain frame of reference
then the time if you have a clock let's
say you are on a rocket okay
and let's say you have two people one is
on earth one is on a rocket that's going
to take off from earth now the rocket's
velocity is going to be very high in
order to escape the earth now the clock
which is on the rocket
will seem to proceed at the same speed
if you are sitting in the rocket but if
you are seeing that clock from the earth
then the clock will be going slower so
it is relativistic time dilation the
time that is experienced on the rocket
seems to flow at the same rate that it
is flowing on the planet earth
but it is actually flowing slower
relative to the time on earth that's how
it is so let's say you have two twins
two twin brothers or sisters same age
same everything one stays on earth one
goes on a rocket and spends let's say
one earth year
one year on earth traveling on a rocket
at a very high velocity whatever the
velocity is then when that person comes
back to earth after one year his or her
twin on earth has aged one year but the
person depending on the velocity may
have aged only a few days
so that's how it works so it is
biologically it is everything your
perceived time the time that you
perceive maybe just five minutes on the
rocket if you're on the rocket it may
feel only i only went for five minutes
but if you're on earth that five minutes
for that person may seem like one year
for you so time flows at different
speeds and secondly this also help
happens when you are in the presence of
a
of a mass
so if you are sitting on the surface of
the earth
then time flows at a certain speed but
if you are an astronaut in orbit around
the earth then time flows slightly
differently at a slightly different
speed
it so that's how it goes so to
understand how it actually there is no
intuitive way of explaining it to
understand how this actually happens you
have to look at the equations so if
you're interested you can look into that
but this is just a brief basic overview
of what you experience if you actually
experience time dilation
thank you
thank you so much nice meeting you sir
thank you bye
okay um
let's bring in mr subramanyam
hello hello sir
hi how are you
well i'm speaking from california
all right uh so my question is on uh
so my question is on uh
the recent financial sanctions which was
slapped on russia so it's not just the
government which is impacted it's also
the common citizens
so i feel that you know probably down
the line
in future
probably uh the common citizens might
look
for a decentralized form of finance
because i see that you know probably
some of the credit cards or you know the
banking system might collapse in the
future at least in case of russia
so do you think uh there would be a wide
scale
adoption of crypto
and
would it move from
the asset to the commodity side of
things
yeah that's a good question
right so what you are saying is
absolutely correct when you impose
financial economic sanctions on a
country you're essentially besieging the
country in the old days what you would
have in european countries is every town
every city would have a wall around it
for defense and when the enemy would
come everybody would go inside the wall
and stay inside and try to repel the
enemy uh keep the enemy outside and the
enemy what they would do is they would
besiege the city for days weeks and
months and try to starve the people out
right because if you are inside a walled
city you will soon face shortages of
food of water of other supplies and all
that so they will try to starve you out
and then you will have to surrender that
is what they used to do in siege warfare
when you impose financial sanctions
economic sanctions on a country in the
21st century it is a form of siege
warfare you are starving them out you
are cutting them off from the from the
global economy you are slowly starving
them out and the people who are the
worst hit in
during economic sanctions are the
civilians the government the elites they
are never really hurt it is the common
man woman and child who suffer the worst
so that is the brutal reality of of
economic sanctions and the people who
impose economic sanctions know it it's
going to affect the innocent people the
most and and that's just how it goes
there is no compassion or sympathy in
the world
now like you said
possibly one way of circumventing
economic sanctions is to adopt
cryptocurrency crypto and blockchain
technology and all that because there is
decentralized it is not controlled by
any individual for that we have to be
careful yeah the concept is good
but there are certain cryptocurrencies
that actually are owned they are
controlled by uh by the corporation
let's take bitcoin it is truly
decentralized bitcoin is decentralized
ethereum is not truly decentralized it
is actually controlled by certain
individuals if you know you know so
that's how it is so a truly a proper
implementation of bitcoin technology off
of a blockchain technology if it is done
right then it is truly decentralized and
you will you will actually be able to
use it to circumvent whatever
uh economic sanctions are placed upon
you in case that is done see the real
reason why economic sanctions work is
because the entire global system is
controlled by one entity the entire
global financial and economic system is
controlled essentially by the western
powers essentially by the united states
and they have created this swift system
and all that for for transferring funds
and all that across countries and they
are now trying to cut they're they've
decided to cut russia off from that the
thing is you can create a swift like
system with other countries as well
india could develop its own its own
version of swift in conjunction with the
russians and the chinese if we wanted to
if you want to it's not very hard to do
that it's not some rocket science you
know so you are right i think the world
will in the coming days and weeks and
months and years move towards blockchain
technology truly decentralized
technology because that way you are not
controlled but one has to be careful
that you are adopting a truly
decentralized blockchain uh or
cryptocurrency and not something that
appears to be that but it's not truly
that way so the the the add-on question
to that like something very similar to
that is gold was the standard
so couldn't bitcoin be the standard in
order in order to print money for you
know the different uh federal reserves
that you have across the world
when it comes to bitcoin uh it is not
printable money it's just electronic uh
currency right yeah it could become a
standard if the whole world adopts it
otherwise but the but the people who are
the guardians and custodians of the
current system they don't want that to
happen obviously it is it is going to be
detrimental for to their interests if
the world becomes a decent or
decentralized place so they will try
their best to prevent this from
happening or they may try to hijack the
technology and take and make it their
own so that's what we may see in the
coming days
thank you sir thank you for your time
thank you nice meeting you thank you bye
okay
um
i see that mr putin has come
greetings mr putin
where are you from sir what's your name
i am sushant i am from nasik maharashtra
my question is in one of your videos you
mentioned about a book in which
you know they have
they have said how british or other
foreign powers like portuguese i
introduced a
caste system or rather untwisted
caste system in india so
i'm not able to find that video can you
just
name the book if you remember
here is one book one example
it's called casts of mind
i'm not sure if you can see it
yes yes
of mind by nicholas b dirks
casts of mind by nicholas b dirks that
is one good reference for understanding
what really happened and there must be
some more also i don't remember right
now but i just gave you the reference so
check it out
okay thank you sir
all right thank you nice meeting you sir
thank you bye bye
let's bring in mr wamsi
good evening good day sir where are you
from namaste sir i'm from chennai uh
down south uh from the so-called
dravidian place but
certainly not
so uh
thanks for allowing me so well my
questions are geopolitical question and
as you have repeatedly stated uh it
seems like the the country of the west
is shifting the global order
is starting to change and paths
americana is no longer starting not to
be a reality and the tide is shifting to
the east but so my only question is that
uh this the two strong e civilizations
one being the one being china and the
other being in bharat these are this
true two ancient civilizations and
essentially the globe lauder will either
go to china or to us in the future uh
the company i mean who's going to be the
dominant superpower but with russia now
completely coming under the chinese
geopolitical orbit by because they
depend on china for
economic uh sub i mean like economic
help and all of that because of the
sanctions
they have to be subservient to china
right now so how are we going to tackle
this how are we going to grow in the
next 20 years alone and strong and
come and because we have a legitimate
civilization probably the oldest and the
strongest and the most valuable ones out
there so
yes yes how would we do that
yes yes good question very good question
so the thing is there is no point having
a civilization if you don't have the
means of defending it so that is the
lesson we must learn from the past 1000
years of history now what you have said
is very correct the two old
civilizations the oldest is in india the
second oldest you could say is china
existing ones
and as you are rightly pointing out now
russia is greatly under the control of
china because the americans are cutting
russia off from so what the americans
are doing is they are pushing russia
into the chinese arms
they are right now
in real time in the process of pushing
russia into the arms of china
they are creating a bigger threat than
what the word they would have otherwise
otherwise faced they are essentially
digging their own grave that's what
they're doing so they are cons they are
consolidating the bipolarization of the
world the world could have been a nice
multi-polar place but the americans seem
to want a bipolar
a starkly bipolar world so that's what
they're doing now the question is
obviously about india para and shanghai
jeongvo is china
and india is bharat so
india is still right now a very small
economy compared to china china is
at least
almost six times larger than india
in in economy gdp terms india is about
three trillion dollars and china is
about 18 19 i don't know exactly what
the number is something like that
so india
could easily be subsumed by china if the
things go the way they are going
and now the world is going to be quickly
militarized the germans have announced
that they're going to be spending a lot
more on on defense more than two percent
of the gdp i yesterday said india needs
to double its its military spending it
needs to happen now it is it's very
important so now we're going to see
an increasingly militarized world that
india is now in a difficult position
whether we realize it or not we're gonna
have to find a way of sustaining of
sustaining 10 plus economic growth for
the next 10 20 years while remaining
safe while preventing other people like
essentially china from trying to break
us up
so it's going to be a very very
interesting tight trope walk that we
will have to do the next 10 20 years
there are going to be a lot of
diplomatic balancing we will have to do
balancing of various powers the
americans are right now being very
vindictive towards india because we were
neutral in the
in the u.n security council we did not
condemn the russian actions
which essentially even by remaining
neutral we are siding with russia
actually that's what it means so the
americans especially if you see social
media they're attacking india viciously
right now
so i don't know how long the so-called
alliance or or partnership with america
may last
we have the quad relationship with the
americans and other countries like japan
and australia i don't know how viable it
is in the long run considering the
attitude the americans are showing in
that case india may be on its own in the
coming years
and india still needs to be part of the
global financial economic system which
is controlled by the americans so as you
can see there are big challenges coming
up for india so it is all going to
depend on the indian leadership
how they handle the situation
we're going to need very cool minds and
very mature heads right now mr modi
obviously is very well experienced in
doing all this he he he is he's an old
player in geopolitics in the global
scenario
and after him somebody else
he will eventually retire from his role
as prime minister and somebody else will
come in place in the next 5-10 years
sometime so that person also needs to be
the right kind of person so india is
going to face
intelligence right now the world's been
very nice and cozy it's not going to be
that way
in the 1930s 1940s the world war in a
great deal of chaos
we may see the same sort of again
happening in the coming years coming in
the coming decade perhaps so india has
to be prepared i don't ever have the
right solution i don't have the exact
solution for india's problem the only
solution is india needs 20 years
and high growth high economic growth
because if your economy grows your
military spending can also grow
proportionately and india is going to
need to
uh power up its its military uh defense
forces so that's what what i can say we
need to ensure
somehow that we remain
relatively peaceful and we need to keep
growing at a very high high rate for the
next 10 20 years then we will be able to
and the thing is this
right now the chinese have no respect
for india because india the chinese only
respect one thing which is strength and
power and india is a weaker inferior
nation compared to china economically
and military today if you want the
chinese to respect us and treat us
as equals
we need to rise to that level economic
strength and military strength that is
the only solution in geopolitics the
world respects only one thing strength
and power
that's what india needs to do that is
non-negotiable
next 10 20 years it has to happen then
india will be fine
thank you so much sir hope we defeat the
breaking india forces and india totally
becomes the visual guru
thank you yes we hope that thank you so
much good question thank you
thank you bye
okay
uh whom do we bring in let's bring in mr
rishi
hello
namaste
namaste sir where are you from
i'm from jharkhand
you been here before on this
q a
yes sir
then why did you enter sir i am
requesting everybody please please don't
enter if you have been here before i
want to give the chance to new people
please
please don't just please one question
respect the rules thank you
why why do people do that
let's give a chance to new people
okay let's bring in mr krishna pal
hello hello sir hello sir
hi
hi where are you from
um
all right sir what's your question
so my question is about economic super
power
so how china becomes economic super
going just 20 years
and how can india become economic super
power because of economic superpower you
want something exports
you your experts will be greater than
import and so-called tax dents like m
amazon flipkart twitters microsoft their
ceos are indians
they call them proud indians so why they
can't come to india and make economic
superpower in technology and provide
service to the world
very good question sir very good
question this is one of the most
important questions today right
so like you said china was able to
transform its economy completely in like
20 years or so and how did that happen
it happened because the americans aided
and abetted the rise of china in the
1960s the chinese and the russians the
ussr almost went to war the ussr
leadership had decided to nuke china
they decided to nuke china the americans
stopped them from doing that and and
then they brought the chinese into the
american orbit they allowed the chinese
to become part of the global economic
system and they transferred all of their
manufacturing needs into china so they
the americans deliberately
systematically turned china into a
manufacturing powerhouse
so today all the manufacturing that
america needs is all done in china and
now the chinese have developed their own
technology they've done their own
research r d and they're able to
manufacture anything they want under the
sun
so that the chinese have become a
manufacturing superpower and because of
that they were able to export so much
value to the west and their labor costs
are very used to be very less and that's
how they were able to become this mighty
financial and economic giant the
americans aided and abated the rise of
china right now india
if it wants to become a large economy if
it wants to have
10 plus percent growth of the economy
every year it's gonna have to invest in
manufacturing
it's gonna have to become a
manufacturing giant on its own the some
of the western countries are trying to
decouple from china right now so maybe
they could want to they may want to move
their manufacturing needs into india but
for that india will need to reform its
system and all and become more agile
more responsive and all that so there
are some certain challenges but india
can do that the thing is this
the west the americans
willingly
help the chinese rise this fast very
fast they are not that well dis
predisposed towards india
right the americans have always had a
certain hatred for india whether you
realize it or not and they are not
invested in india they don't want to see
india rise the way china has risen
and secondly they want to use india as a
market as a captive market they want to
sell things to india they don't know
they don't want to buy things from india
so that's why country companies like
amazon etc they are coming into india
and they want to use india as a place
from which they can extract value not
something into which they will give
value so that is the big challenge india
is facing today that's a big challenge
why they come to india and make india
tech giant what will they get in india
are there opportunities for bright
people in india
we don't even have sufficient jobs in
the country yes
this current indian government can
provide that or not
it will take time even if they have the
willingness
to do it they will have to reform the
system the system is rotten it has been
rotten for 70 years
it is built on the foundations of
nairobi and socialism all the systems
are like that there is so much red tape
there are so many regulations the
bureaucracy is horrible to change that
takes a lot of time there is so much see
when you have a nation of 1.3 billion
people any change takes long time even
if you really want to do it there is so
much resistance that you face and these
are the challenges india is facing
so even if the government wants to do
this
they cannot magically create 10 lakh
jobs tomorrow right
it's not possible it takes time so that
is the challenge that india is facing so
it's going to be tough for india in the
coming days and in the couple of decades
but
we have to overcome these problems so
that is the challenge the government
faces today
okay sir
thank you nice nice question
nice meeting you thank you bye
let's bring in mr kishal
hello
hi abhijit it's nice to finally meet you
um i'm speaking from singapore um i'm a
singaporean of the indian heritage sorry
can you hear me well enough
i can i can yes
okay great um so my question is is it
possible to
re-establish a cindy ethnolinguistic
state in india today and if so how and i
asked this question because um
during the partition of india all of the
religiously diverse other states
were cut into two one for pakistan one
for india one for the indic religious
people one for the muslims
bengal and punjab for instance however
when it came to sindh the entire
province was annexed pakistan not a
single portion was left for india you
know and the sindhi hindus were
basically
forced to sort of assimilate and go out
where they could find shelter in india
um
despite sin being so instrumental to the
civilizational consciousness of india
and to some capacity i know that
historically
um this it did say that hey eventually
we will ascend in india but it never
happened but today we still have sin in
the national anthem
so that's my question
yes that's a good question
people don't talk about the plight of
the sindhi people the sindhi people
essentially became rootless they lost
their ancestral homeland
i mean the hindus right so you have seen
these all across india today mostly i
think in western and northern india but
in other places also and they don't have
any place they can call their own they
have simply
adopted various parts of india as their
is where they live
so the question is um can we
re-establish a sindhi homeland in india
it's it's very hard to imagine something
other happening unless we re
unless we liberate
historical sin from the pakistanis and
and make that the real sindh again
because today even if you look at the
region of sindh it no longer has a
sindhi character
if you look at the city of karachi a
hundred years ago it has to be sindhi
and banochi in nature the three
languages that were spoken there were
sindhib gujarati today the language that
is spoken the most is pashto
so what you see is that the demographics
and everything has been re-engineered in
sindh so even if india were to liberate
them there is this we know that there is
this gs in the movement freedom sindhi
freedom movement that's going on in
pakistan
and even if we were to
liberate synth from the pakistani army
still
the demographics that have been put in
place there will be very hard to
alter unless we have a time frame of 200
years
unfortunately
it sounds like you're right yeah
obviously
in india
yes
or establishing india what for that to
happen we would have to clear a part of
india some region of india of all the
people who belong there and then brings
in this in there which obviously is not
feasible it's not practical
it would be unfair to the people who
live there right
so unfortunately the thing is it's not
possible to establish a sindhi homeland
a new sindhi homeland somewhere in india
unless all the cities of india were to
decide
uh
voluntarily to relocate to some some
part of india let's say some some state
of india and establish a kind of
homeland there i don't know if it's even
possible or feasible so it's it's very
impractical unfortunately
i know parts of historic sin lie in
present day gujarat and uh
rajasthan and cynthia is so spoken
you have
you have a significance in the
population in rajasthan and gujarat i
believe it is it is the case but that
has never been historically part of
sindh those regions since has always
been west of kach you know kuch is the
western part of gujarat yes since has
always been historically west of kach so
gujarat have been neighboring states
historically so no portion of synth is
in india today unfortunately that's
that's for this
touch on why this happened why were the
punjabis given punjabi hindus and six
given a land bengal hindus were but the
news were not
it's what the british engineered and the
indian uh so-called leadership accepted
it
just wrong
all right
good question sir nice meeting you
thank you
okay let's bring in somebody else let's
bring in uh
whom shall we bring in
let's bring in mr virat who's been
waiting very peaceful very patiently
hello sir good evening sir
good evening sir have you been here
before
no never
never before excellent i like it what's
your question where are you from first
of all
yeah i'm from ghaziabad uttar pradesh
because
all right all right what's your question
sir
yes my question is what do you think
will be expected from india and russia
in the third world war if it ever
happens uh due to china's attack on
taiwan and
what would be us's response on this
would it be similar to what they
responded to
attack on ukraine will they just cancel
their netflix
account of china people or will they
actually send their troops
so if the chinese were to invade tibet
then there will be an uh outbreak of
hostilities kinetic warfare between the
americans
and the taiwanese on one side and the
chinese on the other side now like i've
said before once warfare starts once the
shooting starts anything can happen it
can escalate other third party is going
to get involved in this
so what is the expectation from india
well
the expectation that people can have
from india is that india should take
should look out for its own national
interest that's the only expectation the
world can have from india
for instance if china were to attack
attack ladakh tomorrow or arunades
tomorrow
can india expect the americans to come
and help us they will not come and help
us
look what look at the way they abandoned
ukraine
right when the russians have invaded do
you think the americans will come and
help india when some something like this
happens they will not
even the russians will not be in a
position to come and help india if the
chinese were to attack lag or arunachal
pradesh or sikkim or something else
tomorrow
so every country needs to look out for
its own self-interest of course the
americans will say we expect this from
india and we expect that from india we
expect support and all that but in the
real world you can expect something only
if you're giving something else in
return and the americans are offering
nothing in return to india so uh
so if
hostilities break out between the
americans and taiwanese on one side and
china on the other side
india will look out for its own
self-interests that's the only thing
they can expect from us so what should
india do if china attacks invades taiwan
india should not get involved in it what
india should do is india should
immediately secure nepal and sri lanka
that's what india should do so that's
what the world can expect from india to
secure its own interests nepal is part
of the indian civilizational sphere so
is sri lanka i am not saying india
should invade and annex nepal and sri
lanka i am saying india needs to secure
nepal and sri lanka you can interpret
secure in any way you want so that is
what india can be expected to do nothing
else
but
sri lankans accept that because we know
that nepal we will not invade we will
not invade sri lanka we will not occupy
sri lanka we will not annex sri lanka or
nepal we will simply secure these
territories that's all all right thank
you that's all thank you for your time
all right thank you bye
let's bring in mr praveen
hello
namaste hello
yes sir what's your question
so my question is basically related to
this what is happening around us so uh
how do you see how do we see this uh
veto thing in the united nation first of
all uh it seems that the united nation
lost his relevance day by day
and we have seen the failures in many
cases in many wars so what is the
significance and then how india should
seek to get first of all the veto and uh
according to you uh
should we actually need that vetoer uh
or just itself it's like not that
relevant because in okay in many
situations in near future let's say we
uh we became strong and we can uh like
uh
go towards deepa then all this part that
we we try to annex in uh india again so
uh
will it help actually or uh it's just
nothing
okay good question the ul united nations
and the veto so the un is essentially a
useless
worthless body
uh in if you look at the uh
if you look at the structure of the
united nations security council you will
see that it reflects the world order
the way it was in 1945 at the end of the
second world war so the victorious
powers in the second world war were
given permanent seats on the un security
council
and india was offered this a permanent
seat
not once but at least twice if not
thrice and our great magnificent prime
minister mr nehru refused the seat on
all occasions and he said please give it
to china not to india and that's how the
chinese became permanent uh
china became a permanent member of the
u.n security council with veto power so
what is veto power it means you can
prevent anything from happening
if if let's say right now the russians
have the veto power there was this u.n
security council resolution that was
tabled that would condemn russia for its
actions in ukraine the russians vetoed
it they were the only ones who we towed
it but the one one vetoes was enough to
to defeat the motion so that's the kind
of power the veto power has india was
given this power india refused it and
today we are suffering the consequences
of that
now the un is essentially a useless body
the only use it has is as an instrument
in the hands of powerful countries so in
the past the americans used to use the
united nations to uh
to condemn various countries and and do
things like that right now the chinese
have infiltrated the u.n and they are
using the u.n for various purposes like
the who so they made sure that the
gohan viruses was called kovade instead
of gohan whatever
and they things like that right so they
are using the un to further their
influence across the world
so that is the uh
that's the use the un has today it is
not uh in it doesn't have any real
powers
it can uh sanction the weak it can hurt
the weak power weak countries but it
cannot hurt the strong countries so if
you want to be uh if you want to be a
significant player in the world you have
to become a strong country that's what i
can say so the u.n india will not be in
a position to become a veto wielding
country nobody will give india the power
today
right
so the only thing india can do is become
so powerful that it's impossible to
ignore india and even if india doesn't
have a veto in in the u.n security
council its economy is so strong that it
has an effective veto in the in the
global affairs so that's the only thing
india can do but nobody is going to give
india
gift india a permanent seat today in the
u.n security council or the veto power
it's simply not going to happen the
chance was there in the 1950s we
we rejected the chance so that's where
we stand now yes so thank you thank you
for uh your brief answer it says thank
you nice meeting you sir thank you for
the question thank you
thank you
bye
all right let's bring in mr
whom do we have
let's bring in mr ashmit
hello
good evening
yes i can hear you have you been here
before no this is my first time okay
first time very nice
question
okay great
yeah so my question is about spin
quantum
electron spin right
yeah what's the question
so what exactly is electron spin either
it is revolution or it is rotation
i'm unfortunately not able to understand
what you're saying sir
electron spin
or rotation
that's at what exactly it is
okay you are asking something about
electron spin what is electron spin is
that people asking
okay what is electron speed so the
electron is one of the fundamental
particles in in the
in the standard model of physics right
and spin is one of the quantum
properties of the electron so the
electron is not a classical object that
you can see it's rotating or so going in
a circle like that it's just some it's
just
a term that we use we also have the
properties of the quarks like you know
we have color charge and all that so it
doesn't mean that actually it has three
colors or something right it's just a
certain term that we use
and the electron spin is a quantum
property of the electron you can have
two configurations spin up and spin down
and that is what we use to construct the
theory of the world that we live in and
it works very well so all i can say in
brief is this electron spin is simply a
quantum property of the electron it has
two values which we call spin up and
spin down you can give it any other name
and it will still still work the same
it's not it doesn't really mean that the
electron is spinning like that you know
it doesn't mean that
all right sir
thank you
all right thank you thanks very much
okay um
let's bring in mr
apramia
hello
hello namaste
namaste where are you
i'm from mumbai
mumbai right what's your question sir
sir i basically have two questions you
can pick whichever
let's just go for one what's your main
what's your best question
um sir when we examine history like uh
if we say
ramayana or mahabharata how do we know
it's not fiction like uh okay how do you
know
from the future how will people from the
future know that harry potter wasn't uh
historical all right the excellent
question how do we distinguish ramayana
and mahabharata from harry potter right
so
let's talk about the mahabharata
in the bawar there are all kinds of uh
events that have supposed to be hap to
have happened
can we correlate those events with
actual geographical places we still have
places in india which are named the same
as the events of the places in the
events of the mahabharata
and so on and so forth right so there is
one clue that we have but it is not
hard clue it's just circumstantial
evidence
but there is another event in the
mahabharata
right in which you have
the great warrior arjun who goes to the
capital city of lord krishna where he
was the king it's called dwarka and he
witnesses the destruction of the city
in a tectonic event in an earthquake and
the city slides into the ocean and it's
swallowed by the ocean and that has been
portrayed as a myth for for all for the
longest time and then when some
archaeologists decided to actually
examine
the seafloor off the coast of the modern
city of dwarka
we found an entire sunken city there
which completely exactly corroborates
what is depicted in the mahabharata
exactly where the the story says that
off the coast of dwarka you will find a
sunken city and you find it there so
that is unmistakable undeniable evidence
that the events are true so if one event
is true we can conclude other events
there's a very high likelihood that all
the other events are also true now
obviously over thousands of years
stories get embellished people who are
very strong and great warriors are
eventually over
if you retell the story thousands of
times they are given what we can
consider to be supernatural powers those
have to be looked at metaphorically not
literally it doesn't mean those people
did not exist
right so that is about the mahabharata
when it comes to the ramayana again we
don't have any we have all these place
names that still exist ayodhya and so on
and so forth but there is one structure
that does exist a man-made structure
between india and sri lanka
so once again there is an event which we
can see
it actually happened and that's why we
have two clues now one from the
mahabharata one from the ramayana that
demonstrate that these events have
bases in actual facts
and if you look at harry potter we know
it was written by a person so here we go
sir
my question was that
if we look at
historical accounts
how do we distinguish them from fiction
like i'm not saying
we need to look at evidence we need to
find actual heart evidence and i've just
told you how we find our
evidence
thank you thank you bye
okay
whom did we bring in we can bring in mr
rahul
hello
hello sir my name is
i'm from merit so my question is
what happens to debt if a nation ceases
to exist
what happens to
to debt
yes
if a nation ceases to exist the debt
also ceases to exist obviously who's
gonna pay it
right that's just how it works very
simple answer if a nation ceases to
exist the debt uh
goes away
if a nation is transformed then the debt
may remain so for instance when the ussr
broke up then all the external debt was
transferred to the nation of russia
which came out of which was the biggest
uh nation that came out of the earth
while ussr but if a nation for whatever
reason ceases to exist the debt also
ceases to exist it cannot be paid back
thank you thank you nice meeting you
all right um
let's bring in
um mr omg
hello hello
namaste namaste where are you from
yes i am from tikamgarh
nice to meet you sir what's your
question
so my question is
that
in future can india be become the
permanent member of the u.n and what are
the competition competiting company
countries
around the globe like after 20 if we see
modern day africa
it's
it's like now india in the 60s or the
50s so
how can we compete with
these type of countries like vietnam and
all
in the upcoming future
okay so the question firstly is can
india become a member of the un security
council how to do it there is no way to
do it
the u.n security council is frozen in
time
the it it represents the way the world
order was in 1945 it needs reforms but
the but the permanent member states
the five permanent members will never
allow reforms so we can keep on
requesting and begging and pleading it's
not never going to happen so there is no
way india can become a member a
permanent member of the u.n security
council a veto wielding member
right so that's not going to happen
there are other countries like germany
and japan etc who also deserve
membership but they will not be given
that india is the
one with the uh
biggest claim but india is not going to
get that thing so
once you miss the opportunity you it
doesn't come back now when it comes to
competing with nations like vietnam
there is no competition vietnam is a
tiny country compared to india its
economy is tiny compared to india
right
yes sir
like the manufacturing hub you said that
the cost labor is also there is also
cheap
yeah so india can take advantage of its
enormous size and scale by making some
reforms in the economy in the in the way
that things are run and make india very
attractive for western nations to move
their manufacturing too it's very simple
make it attractive for them to move
their manufacturing base to india
instead of china or somewhere else
because india has the scale india is the
manpower india has the population and if
india makes it
financially
uh
attractive
and if it makes if it makes it painless
from a bureaucratic red tip perspective
then it will happen and the gentleman
has left
all right
uh let's bring in
mr sujai
sir
so first of all uh happy science day in
advance
uh sir and my question is
uh
uh sir i'm from pune
all right all right
okay uh so my question is uh like uh the
previous uh people they asked about uh
what will happen
you know so if we are supposed to beat
uh china and pakistan etc sir my
question is uh as i told you in your
last video we have to become the 10
trillion economy so as an individual and
as a nation what steps uh should i and
the nation take to make that happen
uh firstly have you been on this video
chat before
no sir no this is my first time okay
okay
okay what steps can the people of india
take
there's nothing the people of india can
take can do unless the government
reforms the system
right what we can do from our
perspective is to uh
remain in india instead of going out to
out to another country the brain drain
let's not do that and try and contribute
whatever we can in whatever way we can
to the indian economy so some of us may
be good at entrepreneurship to start a
business and then manufacture something
in india or or
do something which contributes to the
indian economy to the indian
intellectual capital
or if you
so something like that individuals can
do very less the people who have power
at scale they are the ones like chief
ministers prime minister they are the
ones who are the real power to quickly
change the country and transform the
country but even that is easier said
than done because the system is built in
such a way it's very hard to change but
it's happening we can see lots of
changes happening in the past five seven
years
it needs to carry on and accelerate
further so it's very hard for an
individual to con to contribute
significantly to the economy and to the
country unless you position yourself
toward to a place where you are in a
position of power and you can do things
at scale so put yourself in a place
where you can contribute at scale not as
a single person but at a larger scale
then you can make a difference
thank you sir thank you very much
thank you very much
okay let's bring in
mr siddhant
very nice very nice but what's your
question
sir i have two questions you can choose
which one you have answer
so much first just ask me one question
one question
okay so my question is related to
mr nero our favorite
so he was more or less a
british guy who was like
he was controlled by british but his
policies were more or less
soviet
union oriented which were like opposite
opposing british so why was that
if he was a british guy he should have
okay okay i get it all right okay i get
it
okay what you asking is even though he
was a big anglophile he was educated in
england all that and he was like
culturally british or whatever his
policies were very much
socialist and pro-ussr and you want to
understand why it is so it's because he
was a fabian socialist there was there
is i believe still maybe
in england in the uk the fabian
socialist
fabian socialist party or whatever it's
called fabian socialism movement
so mr nehru was
uh was a member of that
and fabian socialism is all about very
slow incremental change don't do any big
change keep it slow and steady and
incremental
and mr nehru
was a socialist even though he was a he
was an anglophile and that's why from a
from a ideological perspective he found
more closed-less closeness with the ussr
and because the ussr was a socialist
country union of soviet socialist
republics ussr so the word socialist is
there and to his
genius mind he felt that that is closer
to me ideologically than the uk so even
though culturally he was anglophile and
more anglo
uh ideologically he was a socialist and
that's why he found common ground with
the ussr so he tried to emulate certain
aspects
of the uh financial policies of the ussr
but he you can see that the way the ussr
did things was the industrialized to a
very large extent mr nero did not allow
that to happen in india he put in this
uh this neruvian
policies everywhere bureaucracy red tape
and very slow growth and so on so that's
the reason why despite being culturally
english he was ideologically socialist
and more
uh
more similar to the to the ussr right
that's the reason why
so all right sir
both worlds
yes sir yes that's right
thank you thank you nice meeting you bye
okay let's sub
let's bring in dr amit
hello
hello sir hello hello hi i'm a big fan
of your sir so
uh yeah i'm uh talking from kolkata okay
uh i'm a doctor okay and uh
sir i want to tell you one thing that uh
like during this discussion i was
hearing that uh you were talking that if
if we want to defend
china okay we need to
secure nepal and uh sri lanka right so i
want to tell you that uh during my mbbs
days like you know undergrad days i was
uh in nepal i was i i studied in nepal
for eight years okay
so
maybe
like many people will not agree with me
but there is a huge like huge huge huge
anti-indian uh moment is there like uh i
was placed i i my college was in pokhara
okay so if you go from like if you
travel by road
wherever you go you will see anti-indian
slogans and everything so if india wants
to like you know like protect nepal it
will be like you know it will be shown
as as if india is coming to capture
nepal
yes yes
i know you're right
so so so what is the what is the way
like like say suppose nobody told
anything uh to russia you know like like
obviously this ban and everything is
going and i don't think it is not making
much sense so god forbid if if china uh
like you know attacks india tomorrow so
will anyone stop china because you know
in uh past also we have seen that russia
has
a history of like you know taking
china's uh side during last indo-indian
indo china war also so what is the exact
uh scenario that will take place there
okay i get it i get it okay so the first
point that you have raised is very
pertinent that there is a very strong
anti-india sentiment in nepal it's
happened only in the last 20 years after
the maoist takeover of the of of nepal
and the maoist takeover of nepal was
engineered by the indian government of
that exactly exactly exactly exactly so
that's what's happened so all the elite
politicians the so-called political and
social elite in nepal are all jnu
graduates they have all come out of jnu
so they have this entire communist
maoist mindset and the
jnu graduates even in india many of them
have an anti-india mindset so you just
see the same thing in nepal exactly the
entire political um
situation right now environment
ecosystem everything is anti-india even
the education i'm sure they're teaching
anti-india things there so we are
witnessing a whole new generation of
nepalese who brought been brought up
hating india so if india were to secure
nepal india will be portrayed as an
aggressor fine
it doesn't matter how people portray us
we have to do what is best for our
national interest now you if like the
what you said if the chinese were
supposed to supposedly were
hypothetically were to attack india
tomorrow who's going to help india
nobody's going to help india
we cannot
expect anybody to help us that's why we
have to be self-sufficient self-reliant
we already have
the deterrent
see look at ukraine today i don't feel
sorry for ukraine after what they've
done to our students they've been
brutalizing us but
the lesson to learn from ukraine is that
in when the ussr broke up the ukrainians
had soviet nuclear weapons on their soil
it wasn't their possession and they gave
it up and as a consequence we are seeing
what's happening to them today if they
had those weapons with them today nobody
would have dared invade them exactly
india has learned the lessons of that we
have a nuclear deterrent so we have a
certain red line nobody can dare to
cross
so that is one insurance policy that we
do have if you buy in india
but india is having that policy that
they will not uh play like you know put
the first uh like you know first finger
on the nuclear thing yeah yeah do you
understand something words are words
words are just words
we can have a policy we can decide to
change the policy tomorrow after the war
starts
we can change policies any time we have
not signed an agreement with the world
that we will do this no matter what
okay right okay okay words are just
words
so we have the nuclear deterrent and we
need to build up our military
proportionately to the threat that we
are facing today so that's what we need
to do but we have the deterrent which is
a very good thing but but if we if we go
and uh try to secure uh like nepal uh
india like nepal is having a very close
influence to to china okay so suppose if
we proceed even even if we look at nepal
maybe they will go to china and you know
like do like you know maybe that will
start the war we have to consider all
these factors when we do the military
operation or any operation so i'm sure
that indian leadership is taking this in
consideration okay okay all right thank
you thank you thank you so much thank
you to you
okay whom shall i bring in
let's
uh
brindaraka
hello
hello sir i am from hyderabad
and i am really a great fan of you and
my question is thank you
baba
our
father of nuclear our father nuclear
scientist was killed by cia
so if he had been alive
so how much we could have advanced in
our nuclear technology was seeing a
video just now that
our
we don't possess
what we say nuclear uh submarine
technology
so even uh now we have i think uh made
the nuclear uh
submarine reactor but it is not as
efficient as america's
so if he was alive uh how much we could
have grown okay that is my question
okay first of all yeah good question sir
firstly we don't have any evidence that
was killed by the cia
it may be so but we don't have any hard
evidence that can prove that okay you
never have the proof for that now the
question is like you said we we are
developing a nuclear submarine a
miniaturized nuclear submarine that we
can fit into uh i'm sorry not submarine
we are developing a miniaturized nuclear
reactor that can fit into a submarine
we are in the process of developing it
the first time you develop a technology
technology it's not going to be
efficient enough the americans have been
doing it for decades the russians have
been doing it for decades we are only
doing it now so it will take multiple
iterations of improvements before we
have a really good
nuclear reactor that can
be installed in a submarine right now we
will do whatever we can with whatever
reactor we have it's still working it's
still something that can power an actual
submarine so it takes time so it's not
about whether mr baba was alive or not
it's about the fact that we started this
development process only very late
right so that's the first thing now mr
baba is not the only person who
developed the indian nuclear weapons
under the indian nuclear program we have
lots of brilliant scientists who have
never been mentioned by name only some
people get the prominence
for instance people i see i am not
saying mr baba was not a good scientist
or anything but only some people get the
limelight and they are highlighted you
think the nuclear weapons program
depended only on one person that's
simply not the case see nuclear science
nuclear physics is not a very very very
hard actually you know it's actually
quite straightforward once you once you
have the manpower the the money and all
that you can
quickly reasonably quickly develop a
working nuclear reactor it's not very
hard to do that
so
uh mr baba died in some time in the
1960s but we had lots of other
scientists who carried over the work
forward so i don't think the death of
one individual
has a big effect
on the entire program which depends on
lots of individuals who are all equally
intelligent
right he's not the only guy who was
making who's developing nuclear reactors
there were lots of people are doing it
he was simply the guy in charge of the
thing the administrator administrators
are not actually doing science they're
just overseeing the administrative and
managerial work they're managing the
process
for instance people say that doctor ap
jabul kalam developed all the indian
nuclear missiles himself
he was just simply in charge of the
program he was a great scientist no
doubt about it but he's not the guy who
built all the missiles himself there
were lots of people working under him
who actually did the work of course he
was guiding them he was giving them
directions and of course he was a great
scientist it doesn't mean that he did it
himself it's always a team effort when
you are building technologies like
nuclear reactors nuclear submarines
missile systems lots of people are
involved in that and only one or two
people get the highlight get the
limelight so we have to understand that
the loss of one individual even if it is
done as an assassination does not have a
long-term effect as long as all the
other individuals are able to do their
work
right yes so one more question
yeah one question
just one suggestion if we
uh
if the iits are
the iit students if we ban them for like
ten years or five years from going
outside of the country can we
you know bolster the brain in brain
drain which is going out we can can we
start you know you can you can you can
keep people in india at gunpoint it
doesn't mean they will contribute
anything to india
we have to develop our own uh
we have to make sure that everybody has
a job that we can offer to them in india
right right now we're not we don't have
that so all right
thank you thank you sir thank you thank
you
okay let's bring in
mr anuj
hello
hi sir i have been a great fan of yours
ever since
so
i have something some questions for you
sir
um please ask me only one question and
please state where you're from
i am from
pradesh
yes
so sir we were familiar to this concept
of deep state when it comes to america
yes and and this this this concept of
has been shattered in pieces where ever
since this bad administration has took
over the command
sir um
um
as you know that in afghanistan they
they they just abandoned the
billions of dollars of stuff means
helicopters
helicopters missiles and everything just
it did
means their common sense didn't uh poke
them that you should
get that back to your motherland you
know so this reluctance to this uh this
the
this this this uh dharma their part of
doing work
they have been
there they are off track means
and also they are their statements of
their foreign
their
as as you know that there are very
various there are various spokespersons
that they have
for their foreign
giving advice to foreign
my question is that uh
is deep states gonna break or
what what do you see the future of this
uh of the
world hegemony
in future when it comes to america and
who's gonna take power means
specific to america
yes okay so what you're asking is is
america going to remain the sole
superpower in the world will they keep
on controlling the world in the future
yes what we are what we are witnessing
right now
in the light of the events in ukraine
what we are witnessing now is that first
of all the americans abandoned
afghanistan when it was no longer
suitable for them they no longer had any
interest in their abandon afghanistan to
the taliban and they left behind
billions maybe i don't know 100 billion
may be worth yeah remember the exact
figure
so therefore economy of people yes
yes more than 85 billion dollars worth
of weapons they left behind in
afghanistan and the kind of weapons that
left behind
you need specific training to be able to
use those weapons the taliban don't have
the training so eventually those weapons
will make their way
into the hands of the isi so essentially
they left behind a donation for pakistan
the americans the abandoned afghanistan
and now they have also abandoned ukraine
when the russians have invaded so what
we are witnessing right now in real time
is the beginning of the decline
of
this supremacy of the west essentially
the us in the world the world is
becoming very quickly bi-polarized it
was a multi-polar world until now lots
of middle powers and strong powers now
everything is shifting in two directions
one is the western side the americans
and their their minions and on the other
hand we have nations like china and
russia and whoever are there their
minions and some nations
are stuck in between for instance india
not quite sure where we can go we need
the americans against the chinese but
the americans are right now being very
vindictive towards india right
and uh we cannot be on the side of china
because they they want to break us up so
that's where we are right now so we are
witnessing a very rapid shifting of the
geopolitical balance of power we are
witnessing the emergence of a bipolar
world and we are witnessing the
beginning of the decline of american
hegemony over the world 20 years from
today it is quite unlikely that america
will be in the same position where it is
today it may have declined significantly
and so so would have europe possibly
europe would be at war who knows so we
are witnessing these events in real time
so we have witnessed in the decline of
the west
all right
how how decisive does the position of
president becomes when it comes to
geopolitics around the world means of
okay how many additional questions do
you have yes
no sir i have just one one request for
you american native americans if you
have any if you okay if you have
suggestions or requests please put them
in the comments below okay all right
thank you thank you thank you thank you
much
thank you bye
okay let us bring in mr
shekhar
hello hello sir
use respect for you first of all
thank you thank you i'm on your channel
for the first time
and uh nice to meet you um yeah i'm from
bangalore i'm a software engineer my
question is regarding uh the realities
of the life
uh
for last like one one and a half year
i've been uh
like going through a lot of articles and
going through a lot of podcasts some
documentaries
on this concept of theory of simulation
so i want to know your views are we
really into a simulation
i have spoken to some religious person
also about it i was talking to some some
atheist people
also about it but they they all have
different different views like in the
indian hindu theology also there's
something called
the same kind of concept is like you
know
it's like we are into a simulation so
what is what is your visa on this
yeah a very good question the thing is
if you are inside a simulation so what
is the simulation hypothesis it means
that let's say you have a very powerful
super computer that you can program so
if it is powerful enough you can create
life in that supercomputer that evolves
on its own you can create an entire
universe inside that a simulated
universe and then you may see the
emergence of stars planets even life
there so that is like
like creating a game and giving
artificial intelligence to the character
inside the game
exactly if your computer is powerful
enough then it will be able to create
artificial intelligence artificial life
all of that inside the simulation itself
so if you are
so what it means is that we ourselves
could be inside a incredibly powerful
super computer which is able to simulate
an entire universe our intelligence our
life everything
and then how do we know whether we are
actually inside a simulation or not so
according to this framework of a
powerful supercomputer that can create a
simulation that's this good then it is
certainly possible that the universe
that we see
could be a simulation it is certainly
possible but if you are inside it there
is no way of knowing whether you are in
a simulation or not there is no way of
knowing it yeah but the theory of
simulation gives such a strong point of
view which like you know like matches
our reality like yes we we believe that
our creator some people call it god our
creator we don't have any option to
contact our creator the similar way
if i create a game and i create a
character in the game and provide that
character into artificial intelligence
intelligence that character will will
have no means to contact me which is his
creator
so
so these kind of you know it confuses me
that
whether i am a simulation or whether
it's a real real life
there is there is no there is no need to
be confused because there is no way ever
that we can find out whether we are in a
simulation or not let's say you create a
game character who you have created that
game character even if he or she is
artificially intelligent there is no way
that that character can ever contact you
or even know that you exist right
correct similarly if we are in a
simulation there is no way that we can
know it so there is no way there is no
point torturing ourselves wondering
whether we are in a simulation or not
but that is nothing new
but but the character will be always
confused as you know somebody would have
created us and somebody is our creation
we call it our god they call it dog
something like that opposite of
there is no way we can ever
possibly find out whether we are in a
simulation or not so we will never know
the answer then what's the point of
being confused and tortured don't think
about it because there is no way we can
find out
there is no way we can find out
right nobody has the answer not even the
brightest scientist in the world is
answer
and on top of that the movies like
matrix and all it confuses me again more
further i go i feel that i'm more deep
into the rabbit's hole like that so
yeah the deeper you think that more
confused you will get so it's up to you
what you want to think what we think is
what we can control right okay okay
thank you
been nice talking to you interesting
question man nice meeting you thank you
thank you
have a good day bye thank you bye
okay let's uh bring in whom shall we
bring in let's bring in sanjana
miss sanjana good evening
hello
yeah so um one question that i have is
that we as a country india is facing
like two enemies right now one is china
and one is pakistan but pakistan has
like so many deaths and it's under a
very big like economic strain right so
it is going to disintegrate and break so
is it actually a two-pronged uh
you know is it actually that
a severe threat from pakistan because
the people inside it are really in a
very bad place right now correct with
the whole economic strain and they're
having and they're taking money from
china which is like you know their
interest is like death we all know that
yeah
and things like that so you know that's
what i wanted to put that situation that
you know is it like
if pakistan disintegrates then what
would that mean to india and you know
about the whole
things that's happening in the area
okay okay very good question so you said
we have two threats one is china one is
pakistan i would say we have more than
two threats there are certain unseen
threats that we don't even know about
that most people cannot see
the global order is controlled by
certain forces who may not be very
favorably inclined towards india they
don't want india to rise right so there
are other forces that may not be that
visible and that apparent
the apparent forces are china and
pakistan now pakistan essentially is not
a country that is stable on its own it
in usually in a country like india the
country has an army in a country like
pakistan the army has a country
it's the other way round
right so if the army is neutralized the
country will disintegrate they don't
have anything in common which holds them
together apart from the army keeping
them together of course they have a
common religion but you as you know
there is a lot of strife even within
that that religion inside the country
and so on and so forth so pakistan
it is held together right it was held
together for many decades by the
americans they were supporting funding
financing pakistan for various purposes
now the americans no longer have a use
for pakistan
now the chinese are using pakistan and
both these countries have used pakistan
to destabilize india the americans were
funding pakistani terrorism in india for
decades now the chinese are doing the
same thing they want to keep india
counter-balanced by using pakistan as
the as the stick to beat india with so
if india wants to solve the pakistan
problem it needs to also solve the china
problem
so india has two visible threats but it
also has certain unseen threats that if
you can't see we can't talk about so
india i mean the world is very complex
india has multiple challenges the
solution for india as i keep saying is
to grow its economy become a major power
then
once you are strong enough powerful
enough the chinese will be scared of you
and they will respect you and then we
can deal with pakistan also so that is
the solution which we need to implement
in the next 10 20 years
all right yeah
yeah i think i get it thank you so much
thank you so much nice meeting you thank
you yeah bye
okay let's take one
final
question
let's take one final question
home shall i bring him there are 10
people waiting i'm so sorry guys only
one will be picked let's bring in mr
saita yes
okay
so sir i'm actually a teenager and
looking at the situations that are
happening in russia and ukraine
and the major point is that india needs
to be very economically at a higher
state so to be
considered as a very stable and powerful
country so being i'm actually getting
worried about my future uh because i'm a
team so i'm
i'm thinking of prospects future
prospects to which i can look for in the
future so my question is i'll actually
read the question my question is what
should an ideal team
what should ideally be indian teen
indian teenagers
look aim for in their future like which
sectors or which type of
which type of job opportunity should
they look for keeping both the aspects
of
success for themselves and and also
contributing to the uh
contributing to the contributing to the
sector india
uh
india becoming a superpower like that
good good good very good question so you
know what every teenager every human
being is different everybody has certain
strengths certain weaknesses certain
aptitudes and certain things they can't
do so i don't know you personally right
because i haven't seen you only for 30
seconds so i don't know what are your
strengths your aptitudes your likes your
dislikes every person is unique and
you all have everybody has certain
strengths so what every teenager needs
to do is try to understand yourself find
out what are your strengths
work on those strengths and make those
strengths stronger right so let's say
i'm just guessing let's say you're good
at software development or you're good
at coding let's say then acquire as many
skills as possible in that field you
will have to go through the education
system get whatever degrees because
that's the way the world works but in
the 21st century what really matters is
real skills that you can really use to
build things in the real world
so acquire skills as much as possible
and and make sure that once you are out
of the education system spend the at
least the first 10 years of your adult
life
developing yourself financially
and and gaining as much experience
and skills as possible so the first 10
years at least don't think don't worry
about the family the country all that
focus on yourself because if you bring
yourself to a higher level where you can
make a real difference then you can
really help the country let's say you
are earning one lakh rupees a month and
you want to give 10 percent to the
country you can give only 10 000. but
let's say you're earning 1 million
dollars a month you can give much more
so make yourself strong enough where you
can do that so at least 10 years out
after you're out of the education system
focus on yourself only on your career on
your experience on your growth
then
when you are experienced enough then you
can contribute something to the country
so that's a
broad roadmap i could give you right
so by contributing you mean by taxes or
something like that
any way you can maybe by taxes or maybe
by starting a new company in india or
maybe by doing something contributing in
some in in investing or in some
economic sector or whatever you can once
you once you have spent 10 years gaining
experience you will know what it means
to contribute exactly right yes thank
you sir thanks for choosing me all right
the last one nice meeting you thank you
thank you thank you
okay people people this is the end of
today's session i apologize to the
people who are waiting i'm very sorry
very sorry it's always
i'm never gonna run out of people
shall i bring in one last person okay
let's bring in mr vikas last final
hello
and he's gone
sorry what's gonna happen
okay
anyway let's bring in one more person
let's bring in
sorry hello sir how are you doing
i'm doing very well
i'm just so excited i feel like i'm
meeting a celebrity
i'm not a
celebrity think that way
all right sir i'm from america i've been
watching your podcast for quite a while
and i've showed my brother as well
uh everything that you say is very
interesting and it's probably some of
the most clearest information i've ever
received
um thank you
my question sir is that you've talked a
lot about you know india's um
political
advances strategy
successes and fails
through you know russia china
many parts of asia middle east
europe america
but
what how do you see india when it comes
to let's say places like south america
or africa
um for example like um
i've recently read that
possibly china was extending
its
hands in the caribbean where barbados
was uh
you know used to be under the um
imperial rule of
of england and they then they got their
independence but they were still a
commonwealth under um uk
and uh they had um they you know like
they recently now are no longer
commonwealth they're a republic but many
uk representatives are kind of upset
they think that china is pushing out
uk's influence and now china's in
influence is over there so but so how do
you see india's influence in the future
and how do you see this play out
in south america in caribbean islands or
in ireland south or in africa
that's a very good question so you find
you will always see this with this
tussle this this uh
uh this wying and jousting for influence
all across the world among the major
powers so in the past what you had was
the anglo-sphere dominated the world it
was the british empire first and now you
have the american uh
the american superpower the american the
u.s is also an empire in a sense we call
it a superpower but it's an empire it
has interests all across the globe it
has influence all across the globe
commercial interest financial interest
economic interest and so so much so much
more
and that is also something you we see in
south america in the caribbean in africa
now what you are witnessing in the last
10 years or so is that the chinese are
making inroads into the south american
sphere into brazil into argentina they
are setting up industries there they are
they are
tying with the tying up with the
government in various sectors they're
also focusing greatly in investing in
africa they're setting up industries in
africa they are essentially buying out
african countries buying mines buying
commercial estate and much more and it's
essentially no contest when it comes to
africa because the europeans and the
americans don't have don't seem to have
much of an interest there in africa is
so resource-rich
the chinese are moving there and they
are they are essentially taking over the
continent the africans can see it but as
long as you the chinese like like
somebody said they are very adept at the
art of the bribe they can essentially
purchase entire countries by bribing the
right people so that's what's happening
when it comes to india
india is doing none of these things thus
far india is still a small economy three
trillion dollars
yeah i see india doesn't try to bribe
many countries
and not bribing but i see that india
doesn't really do a whole lot of like um
i'm not even say propaganda but we we
unfortunately don't try to promote
ourselves on a wide scale culturally
it's very ground ruled work it's very
much people like you and myself and
other people that are trying to promote
india trying to spread our culture you
know all the positives and things like
that but it's it you don't see like wide
scale stuff from the indian government
promoting india so what's the yeah so
what's lacking first of all is is an
effective diplomatic outreach india's
diplomatic core if you look at it it's
1700 strong we have in india one
thousand seven hundred diplomats which
is smaller than the diplomatic core of
singapore
so for some reason india hasn't even
onboarded sufficient diplomats to have a
proper proper outreach with all the
countries in the world so that's one
sphere in which we are so lacking so so
visibly so what india needs to do is we
need to onboard people into the
diplomatic core from various uh
backgrounds scientists uh engineers uh
people from the academic sphere
international relations and much more
and that's what we could use to to do an
effective outreach with different
countries in africa in
south america and so on and india hasn't
taken the initiative to do that india
also hasn't established trade relations
or or
investment relations in south america
and all in africa
we know that there's there are so many
resources there so for some reason india
has thus far not done enough in this
aspect the chinese have stolen a march
over india right so that's something we
need to address
so i recall that when um india during
the pandemic it did a lot of work like
in you know humanitarian aid and also
sending a lot of vaccine to south africa
and also to brazil i mean some of the
poorest country got it for free some of
the other folks you know they had to pay
for it but still it was faster than
getting faizan pfizer and moderna which
you know you you know that you have to
keep in certain sub-zero temperature
which not every country has the faculty
to do that for their millions and
millions of citizens
so do you think like india needs to do
more
um is it more outreach or is it also
like you said like china is buying up
land you know doing all this uh factory
and promotion and and uh business-wise
like what what what um what what what
like can we stand on
we need to do everything
we need to have the kind of operating
outreach you just mentioned you know
humanitarian assistance we also need to
send our uh
to send our entrepreneurs to to invest
in various countries across the world in
south america set up shop there set up
shop in africa and we need a more
effective diplomatic policy to have a
proper ties with various countries and
their leaders their elite
and so on so we can you have
people-to-people contacts we can have
indian entrepreneurs go into various
african countries set up businesses
there and india can benefit from that
even in south america so there's a whole
lot that can be explored i mean the sky
is the limit right because i see that
like many south african and south
american nations
i mean not of course every country wants
to be prosperous and but that doesn't
they don't seem like they're all very
much geared towards war and taking power
in an extremely aggressive and
regressive way
you know compared to as you were saying
many other european influence i mean yes
america likes to say that we are our own
country and not that they are not but
again they're also under the power of
influence of their ancestors and how
they were of how they did things you
know so i do see that in the future
india can have very friendly
relationship with many south um american
and african countries uh it was just
curious as to how we can reach out and
what we what could be yeah like i said
we need to have a multi-pronged outreach
we can use all of our strengths to reach
out to various countries and establish
all kinds of relations okay all right
all right ma'am thank you nice meeting
you thank you you too sir it's been a
pleasure
thank you thank you bye
all right ladies gentlemen friends
everybody this is the end of today's
session it was very interesting
and i will see you very soon all right
all right
take care everybody and we shall
continue doing this great fun
take care
bye